Finding Aid for College of Literature, Science and the Arts Honors Program (University of Michigan) records, 1957-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
College of Literature, Science and the Arts Honors Program (University of Michigan) records 1957-1984
University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science and the Arts. Honors Program.
0.5 linear feet
97116 Bimu 2
Program established in 1957 within the College of Literature, Science & the Arts designed to provide a rigorous curriculum for exceptional students. Early directors include Robert C. Angell and Otto Graf. Records include correspondence, course material, schedules and topical files relating to the administration and development of the honors program.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records of the Honors Program (donor no. 7791 ) were received in 1990.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open to research.
In 1957, the College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A) established the Honors Program to provide freshman and sophomores with the opportunity to pursue more scholarly options. Honors courses had already been available for juniors and seniors through the various departments, however, the university felt that new exceptional students were being neglected and therefore attending other institutions that did offer four-year honors programs. The main objective of the Honors Program was to attract superior students to the University of Michigan.
With Robert C. Angell at the helm, an Honors Council comprised of representatives from LS&A departments participating in the Honors Program was formed to develop the curriculum guidelines. The program was designed to ensure a liberal arts education, yet allow students the flexibility to create a program of study based upon their personal interests. In addition to more challenging courses, honors program students were offered special counseling by members of the Honors Council, lodging and camaraderie with others who emphasized academics, extra credit for summer reading, and the opportunity to write a thesis. Top high school seniors were then issued invitations to join the program based on their high school grades, test scores, and a personal interview. Eighty-seven student chose to participate that first year.
Otto Graf followed Angell as director of the program in 1961. Six hundred students were then participating in the program, creating a small college atmosphere within the expanse of the larger institution. Although, the program was an official success, controversy arose in the early 1960s concerning the special privileges afforded the honors students and the accusations that the course work was not much more difficult than in regular classes.
By the time Jack Meiland took over in 1978, more administrative personnel and staff had been added and issues of concern now turned to the validity of using the same grade standards for honors students as for students taking less demanding courses and using technology to handle the administrative information generated by the program. Meiland continued as director until 1983 when he was succeeded by David Shappirio. In 1991 Ruth Scodel became director of the program.
Directors of the LS&A Honors Program
1957-1961 Robert C. Angell
1961-1978 Otto G. Graf
1978-1983 Jack W. Meiland
1983-1991 David G. Shappirio
1991-1997 Ruth S. Scodel
1997-1998 Micahael M. Martin
1998-2003 Rob Van der Voo
2003-2005 Stephen L. Darwell
2005-2006 David L. Porter
2006- Stephen L. Darwell
The records of the Honors Program loosely document the development of the program and its activities from its inception in 1957 until 1984. The lone Topical series is arranged alphabetically with several folders for Administrative personnel, Awards and scholarships, College Honors Seminar and the Cutcheon Fund. Much of the collection consists of correspondence between the various directors and other campus departments as well as contacts from other organizations.
Information found in the Annual reports folder clearly documents the program's first three years. After that time period, published brochures and brochure copy found in the Brochure folder offer fairly complete information about the program while the Newspaper clippings folder gives an overview of the program's activities and an idea of how the program was viewed by the public. Correspondence housed in the Administrative personnel folders and the Intraoffice correspondence and Miscellaneous folders also offer insight.
The remainder of the record group contains lists of Honors Council members, some routine office transactions, procedure guidelines, and opportunities within the Honors Program that shed some light on the program's direction. For an idea of student interest in the early 1980s, see the folder titled Fund requests in the Cutcheon Fund folders. Project proposals are attached to each fund request. Also of special interest is correspondence related to Offset a short-lived literary magazine which was developed and produced by honors students.
For additional information regarding the Honors Program see the College of Literature, Science and the Arts record group, which also contains Honors Program records. The records of Robert C. Angell are also held by the Bentley Historical Library.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science and the Arts. Honors Program.; Universities and college--Honors courses.; Angell, Robert Cooley, 1899-1984; Graf, Otto.
- Topical
  - Administrative forms (Honors Program specific) 1979-1982 (Box 1)
  - Administrative personnel
    - Angell, Robert C.
      - Biographical 1958 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1957-1959 (Box 1)
    - Graf, Otto
      - Biographical 1964-1966 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1960-1974 (Box 1)
    - Meiland, Jack, Correspondence 1981-1983 (Box 1)
    - Morrow, Margot, Correspondence 1979-1983 (Box 1)
    - Shappirio, David, Correspondence 1983 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - Awards and scholarships
    - De Roy Professors 1980-1983 (Box 1)
    - Harry S. Truman Memorial Scholarship 1983 (Box 1)
    - New Honors Student Scholarship Program undated (Box 1)
    - Ruth Sinclair Memorial Award for Honors Counseling 1980 (Box 1)
    - Sophomore Honors Award 1980 (Box 1)
  - Brochures 1959-1983 (Box 1)
  - Budget 1979 (Box 1)
  - College Honors Seminar
    - Harold Stein 1960-1962 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Course schedules 1969-1983 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Cutcheon Fund
    - Description undated (Box 1)
    - Fund requests (Thesis proposals) 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Database project 1979-1984 (Box 1)
  - Honors Council and counselor's lists 1958-1973 (Box 1)
  - Intraoffice correspondence 1982 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1957-1969(includes photographs) (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings 1957-1978 (Box 1)
  - Offset literary magazine, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - Press releases undated (Box 1)
  - Procedures 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Remodeling 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Statistics 1980-1983 (Box 1)
  - Student recruiting 1957, 1980-1984 (Box 1)
  - Study abroad 1982-1983 (Box 1)